Finding Aid for Upjohn family papers, 1795-1916
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Upjohn family papers 1795-1916
Upjohn family.
86133 Aa 2
Papers collected by Robert U. Redpath and Richard U. Light of the Upjohn family of upstate New York and western Michigan, founders of the Upjohn Company. Daybooks, daily journals, sermon notes, and journal of trip to America and on the Erie Canal in 1830 of William Upjohn.
3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Robert U. Redpath (donor no. 5194 ) and Richard U. Light (donor no. 5751 ).
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
William Upjohn, born June 10, 1770 in Shaftesbury, England, was a surveyor, land agent, appraiser of timber, and Methodist lay preacher at St. Rumbold's Church in Shaston. In 1796, he married Mary Standard, and from their union would come nine girls and three boys. In the mid 1820s, with England in the midst of an economic depression, William sent two of his sons to American to explore the possibility of moving there. They stayed two years, then one of the sons -- Uriah -- returned to recommend that the family immigrate. Arriving in New York, William and his sons William and Uriah immediately set out to examine farm and mill properties in upper New York State. The family spent the winter of 1830-31 in Hyde Park, then moved to the town of Greenbush near Albany. They eventually settled in Pittsford, a suburb of Rochester.
While there, Uriah and the younger William started and completed their medical education at the College of Physician and Surgeons at the New York Hospital, graduating in 1834. After spending a year helping their parents with their farm, the brothers came to Michigan, eventually settling in Richland. William later moved to Hastings. The elder William never came to Michigan. He died August 26, 1847.
His sons would flourish. William, in addition to his medical career, would serve as Regent of the University of Michigan. During the Civil War, he served as Surgeon-in-Chief of the First Brigade of the 1st Cavalry Division of the Army of the Potomac. He died August 2, 1887.
Uriah Upjohn would prosper as a physician. Many of his children would attend the University of Michigan where they received training in medicine and allied fields. Henry graduated in 1871; May and Amelia received degrees in the School f Pharmacy also in 1871; Helen received her medical degree in 1872; and William his degree in 1875. Two of them, William and Henry, would become partners in the Upjohn Pill and Granule Company, based in Kalamazoo. The other two brothers Frederick and James would shortly join the company. Their company would grow into the Upjohn Company.
This collection, accumulated by Robert U. Redpath and Richard U. Light, consists largely of papers of William Upjohn, born in England, who migration to New York in 1830. Much of the material dates from before the passage to America, and includes sermons, daybooks and journals, and material relating to his work as surveyor and timber appraiser. The materials after 1830 concern his passage to his eventual home in upper New York State and to his business endeavors. Of interest is a folder of the minutes of the Greenbush Debating Society in 1833. In addition, there is a series consisting of papers (mainly photocopied) of other family members, including correspondence, Civil War materials, and miscellanea. A final series is comprised of various medical volumes owned by Upjohn family members.
Subjects:
Debates and debating.; Erie Canal (N.Y.); Frontier and pioneer life--Michigan.; Greenbush Debating Society.; Kalamazoo (Mich.); Timber--England.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1811-1820.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1821-1830.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1831-1840.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1841-1850.; New York (State); Voyages and travels.; Upjohn Company.; Michigan--Social life and customs--19th century.; Upjohn family.
Contributors:
Upjohn, Uriah, 1808-1896.; Upjohn, William, 1770-1847.; Upjohn, William, 1807-1887.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Sermons.
- William Upjohn journals and other materials
  (collected by Robert U. Redpath and Richard U. Light)
  - Letters exchanged between William Upjohn and Mary Standard 1795-1822, originals and photocopies (Box 1)
  - William Upjohn notes and letters written before sailing to America June-July 1830 also sermon outlines, originals and photocopies (Box 1)
  - Letterbook-religious notebook 1812-1814 (Box 1)
  - Daybooks and journals
    - 1812 (Box 1)
    - 1814 (Box 1)
    - 1821 (Box 1)
    - July 1824-1825 (Box 1)
    - 1826 (Box 1)
    - Erie Canal Journal, October-November 1830, 2 folders (Box 1)
      (versions include original and later re-copying)
      (microfilm copy also available)
    - 1832-1834 (Box 1)
    - 1834-1835 (Box 1)
    - October 1842-January 1844 (Box 1)
    - April-October 1845 (Box 1)
  - Account book 1828 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of the Greenbush Debating Society 1833 (Box 1)
  - Notes for sermons, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Religious notes (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
  - Timber records 1820 (Box 1)
  - Timber records (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Religious pamphlets, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Printed almanacs 1794, 1823, 1837 (Box 1)
  - Printed miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Book of English maps (Box 1)
- Family papers
  - Family correspondence 1811-1850, undated (Box 2)
  - Family correspondence 1851-1916 (Box 2)
  - Other family, photocopies
    - Hays (Len)-Esther Walton-correspondence 1985-1986 re: family history (Box 2)
    - Journal from England to America (I, II, III), 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Letters
      - Late 1700s-1830 (Box 2)
      - 1830-1849 (Box 2)
      - 1850-1854 (Box 2)
      - 1855-1859 (Box 2)
      - 1860-1862 (Box 2)
      - 1863-1864 (Box 2)
      - 1865-1866 (Box 2)
      - 1870-1880 (Box 2)
      - 1883-1889 (Box 2)
      - Undated (also receipts) (Box 2)
    - Family letters and genealogical materials 1890-1913 (Box 2)
    - Geare (J.N.) correspondence re: Townley estates (Box 2)
    - Lawrence Townley estate (Box 2)
    - Civil War diaries (Box 2)
    - Daybook; ledgers (Box 2)
    - Photographs (Box 2)
    - Drawings (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan Medical School printed miscellanea (Box 2)
  - Uriah Upjohn daybook 1872 (Box 2)
  - Book: The Anxious Enquirer after Salvation... (1858 ?) (Box 2)
  - Book: Compiled volume of religious sermons (Box 2)
- Medical books
  - Volumes used by Upjohn family members in their practice and while attending the University of Michigan Department of Medicine and Surgery, 4 volumes (Box 2)
  - Medical volumes, 6 volumes (Box 3)
Related Material
The library also has a second Upjohn family collection, accumulated by a different line of the family, E. Gifford Upjohn. Valuable biographical and genealogical information will be found in the senior thesis written by Frederick Lawrence Redpath, entitled, "A String in the Fabric: The Story of the Upjohn Family" (Princeton University, April 1939). This volume is available at the Bentley Historical Library. In addition, there is a two volume history entitled Upjohn; A Study in Ancestry and Upjohn; Two Early Journals written by Richard Upjohn Light (1990) also available at the library.